Nicole: User Access control or UAC
is a mandatory access control feature
which was introduced by Microsoft
to improve the security of Microsoft
Windows by limiting user privileges
until authorised by the administrator.
This was done to prevent malware from
compromising the operating system.
User access control generally manages
user accounts particularly those with
special access privileges to protect
against misuse and unauthorised access.
To help keep a system secure, accounts
should only be assigned to authorised
individuals and should limit access to the
minimum level needed by the individual.
Failure to implement an effective
user access control management policy,
may expose an organisations system
to cyber attack as it makes it easier
for hackers to take advantage of
uncontrolled administrative privileges.
One of the techniques used to attack
a system involves the elevation
of privileges by guessing and
cracking administrator passwords
to gain access to target machines.
So, let’s look at how user access
controls be managed effectively?
• By having a user account management
system and privilege management process.
• Not using network and systems
administrator accounts for other
non-administrator activities.
• Restricting privileges to
authorised individuals.
• Set up device-based authentication
allowing only certain devices
to access the network.
• Keeping records of user access permissions
• Implementing a strong password and
unique username policy ensuring that
passwords are changed regularly.
• Restricting the ability to
install third party software
The overall goal of User Access
Control is to protect the system
and maintain the cyber security
of an organisation or company.
It is also used in households
where parents can restrict internet
access to children in the household
but often for different reasons.
It may annoy users that they may not
have full access, but by limiting
access to the absolute minimum needed
to fulfil their role, there is less
chance of cyber attacks happening
therefore making the system more secure.